Let's solve a problem on simple harmonic
motion involving kinetic and potential energy.
An object of mass zero point two kilograms executes SHM
along the x axis with frequency twenty five by pi
hertz. At displacement zero point zero four meters, its kinetic
energy is zero point five joules and potential energy is
zero point four joules. We have to find the amplitude.
The particle performs simple harmonic motion about the equilibrium position. The
total energy is the sum of kinetic and potential energies.
In simple harmonic motion, total energy is equal to kinetic
plus potential energy, which equals one half k A squared.
From the given data, kinetic plus potential
energy equals zero point nine joules.
We know that k equals m omega squared, and omega equals two pi f.
Substituting f equals twenty five by pi, we get omega equals
fifty radians per second, and hence k equals zero point two
times fifty squared equals five hundred newtons per meter.
Now using the relation for total energy, we have zero
point nine equals one half times five hundred times A
squared. Solving gives amplitude equals zero point zero six meters.
Hence, the amplitude of motion is zero point zero six meters.