This animation shows simple harmonic motion and
the variation of kinetic and potential energy.
A particle moves to and fro about
an equilibrium position performing simple harmonic motion.
As the particle moves, kinetic and potential energies vary with time.
Let us understand this mathematically. The displacement of the particle in simple
harmonic motion is given by x equals A, cos omega t.
Omega which represents angular frequency is two pi f.
So we can represent the displacement A, cos two pi f t.
Differentiating with respect to time gives the velocity, v, equals
minus two pi f A sine two pi f t.
Kinetic energy is half, m, v squared, so substituting for, v, we get.
Using the trigonometric identity sine squared theta equals
one minus cos two theta over two.
So we can say that the kinetic energy is proportional to one minus cos
four pi f t over two, which means new angular frequency is two omega.
This shows that the kinetic energy varies with time with a frequency
of four pi f divided by two pi, which is two f.
Therefore, the kinetic energy oscillates with frequency two f.