An object of mass zero point two kilograms executes simple harmonic motion
along the x axis with frequency twenty five by pi hertz.
At position x equals zero point zero four meters,
the kinetic energy is zero point five joules and
potential energy is zero point four joules.
The total energy in simple harmonic motion is
equal to one half, omega squared, A, squared.
Therefore, A, equals square root of two E, over m, omega squared.
Angular frequency omega, equals two pi f.
Therefore, omega equals fifty radians per second.
The total energy equals zero point nine joules. Substituting the values
into the equation gives amplitude equals zero point zero six meters.
Therefore, the amplitude of oscillation is zero point zero six meters.